Welcome to this short video
on how to perform intermittent
catheterization with
Lofric Origo Pro.
Education and training can help
you feel more confident and
enable you to achieve
successful catheterization.
You can use this step by step
video on how to catheterize
with Lofric Origo Pro as support and
follow on from any training given.
Always make sure you follow the
advice and instructions given
by your clinician based on your
individual medical and lifestyle needs.
First, let's briefly go through
the body parts involved in the
urinary system.
Your kidneys are two bean
shaped organs that clean your
blood and make urine.
The ureters are thin tubes that
carry urine from the kidneys
down to the bladder.
The bladder is a hollow,
stretchy organ in your lower
belly that stores urine.
The prostate is a small gland
located just below the bladder.
The urethra is the tube that
carries urine from the bladder
out of the body.
It's completely normal to feel
a little anxious and unsure
catheterizing for
the first time.
Remember that for most men
who perform intermittent
catheterization it's life changing
and surprisingly easy to perform.
With practice and support, you
will soon become more confident.
And intermittent
catheterization will become a
natural part of
your daily routine.
Start and end the procedure by
washing your hands thoroughly
with soap and water.
Hand sanitizer or wet
wipes can also be used.
Remember to clean the
tip of your penis.
Your clinician can advise you on
a recommended routine for this.
Inside the packaging,
there's a sachet with salt
solution you need to squeeze or
press to release
the salt solution.
The catheter is
now ready to use.
Use the loop to
pull down and open.
The packaging has an adhesive
tab on the reverse side,
which can be used to attach
it to a dry, clean surface.
Position yourself by a toilet and
pass any urine if you're able.
Remove the catheter
from the package.
Gently pinch and hold the
sleeve grip to automatically
pull down the protective sleeve.
Use your dominant hand to hold
the catheter and use your non
dominant hand to
hold your penis.
Lift your penis towards the
stomach to straighten the urethra.
Slowly and gently insert the
catheter into the urethra,
holding the catheter with
the protective sleeve.
You may feel some slight
resistance as the catheter
reaches your prostate area or
at the sphincter and entrance
to your bladder.
If you feel a little tense,
find a good position.
Cough a little and
relax. Continue gently.
When urine begins to flow,
insert the catheter slightly
more to ensure a steady stream.
Angle the penis down as urine
begins to flow through the catheter.
Wait until the urine flow stops to
ensure complete bladder emptying.
Slowly withdraw the catheter.
The unique LoFric surface
coating will ensure that catheter is
still smoothly lubricated.
Put the catheter back in the
package and dispose appropriately.
Local regulations may vary.
Your clinician will advise
you on how often to perform
intermittent catheterization
based on your conditions.
This will of course depend
on factors such as how your
bladder works, how often
you have to catheterize,
how much you drink each
day, and other factors.
Remember, LoFric Origo Pro is
a urinary catheter designed to
be used only once.
Did you know that LoFric Origo
Pro can easily be folded and
put in your pocket so you can
take it with you wherever you go?
LoFric Origo Pro
is ready for you,
whatever your lifestyle needs.